If you want to go really deep and really understand
how requests and responses work on the Web,
then this video is for you.
So this is basically a high level overview
of how the Web actually works behind the scenes
in regards to requests and responses.
Now, this knowledge is not required though,
for moving on in the course,
and that's why I marked this video as optional.
So you can safely skip it
if you wanna move on more quickly.
But if you're interested, than just keep watching.
So this is the diagram that we already saw
when we first talked about AJAX calls.
So just to recap, whenever we try to access a Web server,
the browser, which is the client,
sends a request to the server
and the server will then send back a response
and that response contains the data
or the Web page that we requested.
And that's right, this process works the exact same way
no matter if we're accessing an entire Web page
or just some data from a Web API.
And this whole process actually has a name
and it's called the Request-response model
or also the Client-server architecture.
But anyway, let's now dive a bit deeper into this.
So let's use the example of the URL
that we actually accessed in the last video
to get our country data.
Now, every URL gets an HTTP or HTTPS,
which is for the protocol
that will be used on this connection.
And we're gonna talk about this a bit later in the video.
Then we have the domain name,
which is restcountries.eu in this case.
And also after a slash we have to so-called resource
that we want to access.
And in this case, that's /rest/V2 and so on.
Now this domain name, restcountries.eu
is actually not the real address
of the server that we're trying to access.
It's really just a nice name
that is easy for us to memorize.
But what this means is that we need a way of
kind of converting the domain name
to the real address of the server.
And that happens through a so-called D-N-S.
So DNS stands for domain name server
and domain name servers are a special kind of server.
So they are basically like the phone books of the Internet.
So the first step that happens when we access any Web server
is that the browser makes a request to a DNS
and this special server will then
simply match the web address
of the URL to the server's real IP address, all right.
And actually this all happens
through your Internet service provider,
but the complete details don't really matter here.
What you need to retain from this first part
is that the domain is not the real address
and that a DNS will convert the domain
to the real IP address.
And then after the real IP address has been sent back
to the browser, we can finally call it.
So this is how the real address looks like.
So it still has the protocol, but then comes the IP address.
And also the port that we access on the server.
And this port number is really
just to identify a specific service
that's running on a server.
So you can think of it like a sub address, okay.
This port number has nothing to do
with the /rest/V2 resource
that we want to access.
So that resource will actually
be sent over in the HTTP request,
as we will see in a moment.
Okay, and that actually wraps up the first step.
So once we have the real IP address,
a TCP socket connection is established between the browser
and the server.
And so they are now finally connected.
And this connection is typically kept alive
for the entire time that it takes
to transfer all files of the Website or all data.
Now what are TCP and IP?
Well TCP is the Transmission Control Protocol.
And IP is the Internet Protocol.
And together they are communication protocols
that define exactly how data travels across the Web.
They are basically the Internet's
fundamental control system,
because again, they are the ones
who set the rules about how data moves on the Internet.
And don't worry if that sounds confusing,
we are actually gonna learn a bit more about TCP/IP
a bit later in this video.
But anyway, now it's time to finally make our request.
And the request that we make is an HTTP request,
where HTTP stands for Hypertext Transfer Protocol.
So after TCP/IP, HTTP is another communication protocol.
And by the way, a communication protocol
is simply a system of rules
that allows two or more parties to communicate.
Now in the case of HTTP,
it's just a protocol that allows clients
and Web servers to communicate.
And that works by sending requests
and response messages from client to server and back.
Now a request message will look something like this.
The beginning of the message is the most important part
called the start line.
And this one contains the HTTP method
that is used in the request,
then the request target and the HTTP version.
So about the HTTP methods, there are many available,
but the most important ones are;
GET, for simply requesting data,
POST, for sending data
and PUT and PATCH, to basically modify data.
So you'll see that an HTTP request to a server
is not only for getting data,
but we can also send data, now right.
Now about the request target.
This is where the server is told
that we want to access the rest/V2/alpha resource
in this case, remember that?
So we had this in the URL before
and now it is simply sent
as the target in the HTTP request.
And so then the server can figure out what to do with it.
Now, if this target was empty,
so if it was just a slash basically
then we would be accessing the website's route,
which is just restcountries.eu in this example.
Then the next part of the request are the request headers,
which is just some information
that we sent about the request itself.
There are tons of standard different headers,
like what browser is used to make the request,
at what time, the user's language and many, many more.
Now finally, in the case, we're sending data to the server.
There will also be a request body,
and that body will contain the data that we're sending,
for example, coming from an HTML form.
So that is the HTTP request.
And I hope that it makes sense to you.
Now, of course, it's not us developers
who manually write these HTTP requests,
but it's still helpful and valuable that you understand
what an HTTP request and also a response look like.
Also, I want to mention that there's also HTTPS,
as you probably know.
And the main difference between HTTP and HTTPS
is that HTTPS is encrypted using TLS or SSL,
which are yet some are protocols,
but I'm not gonna bore you with these.
But besides that,
the logic behind HTTP requests and responses
still applies to HTTPS, alright?
So our request is formed and now it hits the server,
which will then be working on it until it has our data
or Web page ready to send back.
And once it's ready, it will send it back using,
as you can guess, an HTTP response.
And the HTTP response message
actually looks quite similar to the request.
So also with a start line, headers and a body.
Now, in this case, the start line has,
besides the version also a status code and a message.
And these are used to let the client know
whether the request has been successful or failed.
For example, 200 means, okay.
And the status code that everyone knows is 404,
which means page not found.
So that is where this 404 code,
that everyone already knew, comes from, okay.
Then the response headers are information
about the response itself.
So just like before,
and there are a ton available
and we can also make up our own actually.
And finally, the last part of the response is, again,
the body, which is present in most responses,
and this body usually contains the JSON data coming back
from an API or the HTML of the Web page that we requested
or something like that.
So we talked in great detail
about the most important parts here,
which are the HTTP request and the response.
But in our imaginary example,
we only just did one request to restcountries.eu
and got one response back, right?
And that's how it's gonna work
when all we do is to access an API.
However, if it's a Web page that we're accessing,
then there will be many more requests and responses.
And that's because when we do the first request,
all we get back is just the initial HTML file.
That HTML file will then get scanned by the browser
for all the assets that it needs in order
to build the entire Web page
like JavaScript, CSS files, image files, or other assets.
And then for each different file,
there will be a new HTTP request made to the server.
So basically this entire back and forth
between client and server happens for every single file
that is included in the Web page.
However, there can be multiple requests
and responses happening at the same time,
but the amount is still limited
because otherwise the connection would start to slow down.
But anyway, when all the files have finally arrived,
then the Web page can be rendered in the browser,
according to the HTML,
CSS and JavaScript specifications that you already know.
Now, as a final piece of the puzzle,
let's talk again about TCP/IP
and figure out how this request and response data
is actually sent across the Web, okay.
So we said before that TCP and IP
are the communication protocols
that define how data travels across the Web.
Now I'm not gonna go into a lot of detail here,
but here is what you need to know.
So first the job of TCP is to break the requests
and responses down into thousands of small chunks,
called packets before they are sent.
Once the small packets arrive at their final destination,
TCP will reassemble all the packets
into the original request or response.
And this is necessary so that each packet
can take a different route through the Internet
because this way the message arrives at the destination
as quick as possible,
which would not be possible
if we sent the entire data simply as a big chunk.
So that would be like trying to go through dense traffic
with like the biggest bus that you can imagine.
So probably not a good idea.
Now, as a second part,
the job of the IP protocol is to actually send
and route these packets through the Internet.
So it ensures that they arrive
at the destination they should go,
using IP addresses on each packet.
Okay, and that's it.
That's a broad overview of what really happens
behind the scenes of the Web.
And I hope that you found this information useful
and also interesting and not all too confusing.
But anyway, now let's go back
to our JavaScript and AJAX calls.